Finding Aid for Nursing History Society (University of Michigan) records, ca. 1940-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Nursing History Society (University of Michigan) records 1940-1995
University of Michigan. Nursing History Society.
1.5 linear ft.
89158 Bimu C275 2
Society formed in 1983 with the purpose of engaging in activities directed toward the preservation of the history of nursing at the University of Michigan. Administrative files, 1983-1989, including minutes, programs, membership materials, and reports; and historical files, ca. 1940-ca. 1988, collected respecting nursing history, including class notes, nursing manuals, oral history tapes, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records are the gift of the Nursing History Society (Donor no. 7051 ). Periodic additions are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Nursing History Society of the University of Michigan was officially organized by Linda Strodtman in the summer of 1983, with the purpose of engaging in activities directed toward the preservation of the history at the University of Michigan. The activities of the organization include researching and recording aspects of nursing history at the University of Michigan and educating others about nursing history through the sponsoring of educational programs and the assembling of historical material. Other activities include mounting exhibits and presenting lectures on nursing history.
The records fo the nurisng History Scoiety consist of Administrative files, 1983-1989, including minutes, programs, membership materials, and reports; and historical files, ca. 1940-ca. 1988, collected respecting nursing history, including class notes, nursing manuals, oral history tapes, and photographs. The records have been arranged into three series: Organizational Records, 19821995, Historical Files, 1936-1984, and Audio-Visual Material, 1966-1984.
Subjects:
Nursing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Nursing History Society.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Nursing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Photographs.; University of Michigan. Hospitals.
Genre Terms:
Oral histories.; Photographs.
- Organizational Records, 1983-1995
  The Organizational Records series, 1983-1995, 0.25 linear ft., is comprised of the administrative files of the Society itself. Among materials included are annual reports, meeting minutes and agendas, correspondence regarding Society sponsored programming and the donation of materials, officer lists, program announcements and treasurer's reports.
  - Annual Reports, 1984-1992 (Box 1)
  - Conditions for Loans (Box 1)
  - Donor List, 1983-1985 (Box 1)
  - Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1982-1995, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Officers, 1984-1996 (Box 1)
  - Program Planning and Announcements, 1984-1995 (Box 1)
  - Publications
    - Centennial Calendar, "A Century of Leadership: Nursing at the University of Michigan, 1891-1991" (Box 1)
    - Membership Application Brochure (Box 1)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1985-1995 (Box 1)
- Historical Files, ca. 1936-1984
  The Historical Files series, which spans 1.25 linear ft., contains materials pertaining to the history of nursing, collected by the society. Excepting one folder of issues of the Cadet Nurse Corps News published by the U.S. Public Health Service Division of Nurse Education, and one unidentified photocopy of a letter from 1889 describing war-time nursing conditions, all of these materials relate to the teaching and practice of nursing at the University of Michigan. The bulk of the series is comprised of class notes and instructional materials dating from 1936 to 1962. In cases in which the professor or student of the class whose materials they were was identified, this name has been included in parentheses in the box list below. Also of interest in this series are several nursing handbooks and manuals for use by nurses at the University of Michigan hospital.
  - Alumnae Correspondence and Poetry, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Cadet Nurse Corps News, 1945-1947 (Box 1)
  - Class Notes and Instructional Material, 1936-1962
    - Advanced Nursing Arts (L. Hannig), 1940 (Box 1)
    - Elementary Materia Medica, (L. Hannig), 1940 (Box 1)
    - Elementary Nursing Arts (L. Hannig), 1939-1942 (Box 1)
    - Foundations of Nursing (Amy Hofing), 1960-1961 (Box 1)
    - Maternity Nursing / N360, (Amy Hofing), 1962 (Box 1)
    - Medical Surgical Nursing II (Amy Hofing), 1961 (Box 1)
    - Nurse aides procedures (L. Hannig), 1936-1956 (Box 1)
    - Nurse aides procedures (Mae Simpson), 1945-1954 (Box 1)
    - N320 (Amy Hofing), 1961 (Box 1)
    - N330 (Amy Hofing), 1961 (Box 1)
    - N370 (Amy Hofing) 1962 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous and Undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1889 (Box 2)
    (photocopy of original)
  - Handbooks and Manuals
    - Advanced Nursing Procedures, 1937 (Box 2)
    - Elementary Nursing Procedures, 1937 (Box 2)
    - Handbook for Nurse Aides, 1965 and undated (Box 2)
    - Manual of Diagnostic Procedures for Nurses, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Nursing policy, 1974 (Box 2)
- Audio-Visual Material, 1966-1984
  The Audio-Visual Material series, which spans .25 linear feet, is comprised of two oral history tape reels, recorded in 1966, and photographs of hospital nursing staff, dated 1978-1984, and the 1984 attendants of the Gordon Research Center Proctor Academy in Laconia, New Hampshire.
  - Oral History Tapes, 1996, (2 tapes, 7 inch, 7-1/2 ips and unknown ips (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Nursing Staff, 1978-1984 (Box 2)
    - Gordon Research Conference, Proctor Academy, 1984 (Box 2)